JOSH MEYER

joshua.richard.meyer@gmail.com

jrmeyer.github.io

O in

I work at the intersection of Data, Machine Learning, and open-source language technologies. I've worked in academia, big companies, and small startups, always striving to make Voice tech accessible to all languages and every developer.

Currently based in California.

EDUCATION

University of Arizona July 2019

Ph.D. in Linguistics (focus: Computational Linguistics)

Tucson, AZ

Thesis: Multi-Task and Transfer Learning in Low-Resource Speech Recognition

University of Arizona May 2015 M.A. in Linguistics Tucson, AZ

Seton Hall University

B.A. in Liberal Studies

May 2012

South Orange, NJ

INDUSTRY

Coqui April 2021 — Present

Cofounder & Head of Data

Bringing Voice technologies to all languages and to every developer.

Mozilla Foundation January 2020 — March 2021

Machine Learning Fellow

Advising, building, and iterating on Voice technologies for East African languages.

Artie, Inc. July 2019 — March 2021

Lead Scientist, Speech Technology

Directing and developing all Speech technologies used at Artie.

Mozilla (Machine Learning Research Group)

October 2018 — May 2019

NSF-Sponsored Internship

Developing end-to-end multilingual Automatic Speech Recognition techniques based on Transfer Learning and Deep Neural Networks (i.e. DeepSpeech).

Various Companies

2016 - 2018

Kaldi & ASR Consultant

Optimized Automatic Speech Recognition pipelines for various companies using the Kaldi toolkit.

TECHNICAL STRENGTHS

Computer Languages

Python, Bash, MATLAB, Perl, R, C++ (some knowledge)

Other

 ${\it TensorFlow, PyTorch\ }(some\ knowledge), Kaldi, scikit-learn, pandas,$

nltk, matplotlib, kenlm, Linux, AWS, git, GitHub

OPEN SOURCE WORK

${\bf Mozilla\ Deep Speech}$	Added Transfer Learning	[Code]
Multi-Task Kaldi	Multi-Task Acoustic Modeling with Neural Networks	[Code]
NVDA	Added Kyrgyz language to screen reader	[Code]
eSpeak NG	Added Kyrgyz language to speech synthesizer	[Code]
Autotrace	Created visualization tools for ultrasonic imaging	[Code]

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

National Science Foundation

July 2015 — July 2019

Graduate Research Fellow

Conducting PhD thesis research on Multi-Task Learning and Deep Learning techniques for Automatic Speech Recognition in low-resource data scenarios.

CNRS-LIMSI

July 2016 — July 2017

Chateaubriand Research Fellow

Orsay, France

Conducted research on Neural Network Acoustic Model adaptation, and Recurrent Neural text augmentation techniques for language modeling in Speech Recognition.

American University of Central Asia

June 2015 — August 2015

Visiting Research Scholar

Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan

Created a spoken corpus of conversational speech for the Kyrgyz language.

Arizona Phonological Imaging Lab

Spring 2015

Research Assistant

Tucson, AZ

Developed software to visualize and statistically analyze ultrasonic images of tongue contours for articulatory-phonetics research.

American University of Central Asia

August 2013 — March 2014

Visiting Research Fellow

Bishkek, Kyrgyzstan

Conducted acoustic-phonetic and phonological research on the Kyrgyz language, using paradigms from Cognitive Science.

Arizona Scottish Gaelic Project

September 2012 - July 2013

Research Assistant

Tucson, AZ

Conducted fieldwork with speakers of Scottish Gaelic; Aided in online grammar compilation

Language Acquisition Research Center at Hunter CUNY

November 2011 — August 2012

Research Assistant

 $New\ York,\ NY$

Designed text corpus-based research, transcribed spontaneous child speech, and designed the laboratory's website.

KIT/NYU MEG Lab at NYU

May 2012 — August 2012

Research Assistant

New York, NY

Aided in analysis and processing of Magnetoencephalography (MEG) brain imaging data from cognitive science research.

Language Acquisition and Neurolinguistics Lab at Rutgers

May 2012 - August 2012

Research Assistant

New Brunswick, NJ

Aided in experimental design of Neurolinguistic research studies.

GRANTS & AWARDS

Graduate Research Fellowship

2015-2019

Approx. \$102,000 + \$36,000 (tuition)

National Science Foundation

NSF INTERN Grant

2018

Approx. \$50,000

National Science Foundation

Chateaubriand STEM Fellowship

2016

€5.000

French Embassy to the United States of America

GROW Travel Award

2016

\$5,000

National Science Foundation

Visiting Research Fellowship

August 2013 — March 2014

\$5,000

American University of Central Asia

Regents Scholarship

August 2008 — May 2012

\$111,140 (tuition)

Seton Hall University

PUBLICATIONS

(2020) Ardila, Rosana, and Branson, Megan, and Davis, Kelly, and Henretty, Michael, and Kohler, Michael, and Meyer, Josh, and Morais, Reuben, and Saunders, Lindsay, and Tyers, Francis M., and Weber, Gregor. Common Voice: A Massively-Multilingual Speech Corpus. Proceedings of the 12th Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2020). [Link]

- (2020) Meyer, Josh, and Rauchenstein, Lynn, and Eisenberg, Joshua D., and Howell, Nicholas. Artie Bias Corpus: An Open Dataset for Detecting Demographic Bias in Speech Applications. Proceedings of the 12th Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2020). [Link]
- (2019) Meyer, Josh. Multi-Task and Transfer Learning in Low-Resource Speech Recognition. PhD Dissertation. University of Arizona. [Link]
- (2018) Meyer, Josh. Unsupervised Task Discovery for Multi-Task Acoustic Modeling. Proceedings of the Machine Learning in Speech and Language Processing Workshop. [Poster] [Link]
- (2018) Meyer, Joshua, and Kloehn, Nick, and Carnie, Andrew. The Field is not the Lab, and the Lab is not the Field: Experimental linguistics and endangered language communities. Insights from Practices in Community-Based Research: From Theory To Practice Around The Globe, ISBN: 978-3-11-052701-8 Edited by Shannon Bischoff and Carmen Jany. Mouton De Gruyter [Link]
- (2018) Bekmurzaev, Nurbek, and Lottholz, Philipp, and Meyer, Joshua. Navigating the safety implications of doing research and being researched in Kyrgyzstan: cooperation, networks and framing. Central Asian Survey, 37:1, 100-118, DOI: 10.1080/02634937.2017.1419165 [Link]
- (2017) Meyer, Joshua. Development of a Kyrgyz Speech Synthesizer: A Demonstration of the Ossian Frontend and Merlin Neural Network Speech Synthesis Toolkit. Proceedings of The 5th International Conference on Computer Processing of Turkic Languages, Vol. 1, 130-136. [Link]
- (2016) Lottholz, Philipp, and Meyer, Joshua. 'Friend' or 'Foreign Agent'? On the Limits of Field Research in Post-Soviet Kyrgyzstan. Exeter Central Asian Studies Network. [Link]
- (2016) Meyer, Joshua. Conducting Linguistic Fieldwork in Kyrgyzstan. Arizona Anthropologist, Vol. 27. [Link]

PRESENTATIONS

Language Technologies in Central Asia: A Survey. Joint ESCAS-CESS Conference at the American University of Central Asia.

2017, Bishkek

Predicting Language Dominance in Kyrgyz-Russian Bilinguals. w/ Quam, Carolyn Arizona Linguistics Circle 9. 2015, Tucson

Phonological processing in Kyrgyz-Russian bilinguals. w/ Quam, Carolyn, and Bever, Thomas The Miniconference on Metrical Structure: Acquisition and processing. 2014, Utrecht

The Kyrgyzstan corpus project: Building a language resource unique to Kyrgyzstan and available to all. CASI Public Seminar at the American University of Central Asia. 2014, Bishkek

Now you hear it, now you don't: Phonological processing in Kyrgyz-Russian bilinguals. CASI Public Seminar at the American University of Central Asia. 2013, Bishkek

Psycholinguistics: Thinking about language differently. Lecture conducted at The Platttform at Werkstatttraum.

2013, Berlin

EVENT ORGANIZATION

Kyrgyz Voice Technology Hackathon Attended by undergraduate students as well as professional developers. (2019, American University of Central Asia) [Link]

DeepSpeech & Common Voice Tutorial Delivered to attendees of the Fifth International Workshop on Computational Linguistics for Uralic Languages. (2019, University of Tartu) [Link]

Speech Synthesis Workshop: Hands-on with Merlin & Ossian Delivered to Computational Linguistics Faculty and Graduate Students. (2018, Higher School of Economics) [Link]

Speech Recognition Workshop: Hands-on with Kaldi & DeepSpeech Delivered to Computational Linguistics Faculty and Graduate Students. (2017, Higher School of Economics) [Link]

WRITTEN TUTORIALS

Kaldi Troubleshooting Head-to-Toe	
How to Train $practically$ any Model from $practically$ any Data with TensorFlow	$[\mathbf{Link}]$
Getting started with the Merlin Speech Synthesis Toolkit	$[\mathbf{Link}]$
How to Train a Deep Neural Net Acoustic Model with Kaldi	$[\mathbf{Link}]$
How to add a new language to the eSpeak NG Speech Synthesizer	$[\mathbf{Link}]$
The Flow of TensorFlow: An Email Classification Tutorial	$[\mathbf{Link}]$
An Introduction to CMU-Sphinx Speech Recognition Toolkit: First Steps	[Link]